#### Ahmed A. Alameen

Palestine Street / Near Al-Sakra Intersection Baghdad Iraq

Tel +9647823198733

Email: ahmedalameenahmed@gmail.com



## Personal profile

It's my pleasure to introduce myself ,I'm Eng. Ahmed Alameen , I'm civil engineer and I have master degree in Business Administration From NYIT - Amman. I have full knowledge in:-

Contracts and proposals. Procurement & Supply chain management (EPC project). Project Management (Oil and Gas Project). Offices management Marketing, promotion and sales. Business development. Shipping & logistics, and all management fields and of course in Civil Engineering, also i have full computer knowledge and full language skills in writing and reading. I have moulded into an ambitious, driven and committed engineer. Managing people and inspiring them to work to the best of their ability is one of my skills. Based on my experience I have the ability to work well with people from different background. I have always been a respected and valued member of the teams I worked with and was often entrusted with additional responsibility.

# **Key Skills**

- Good judgment and ability to assess, prepare and implement different strategies related to different tasks, including tasks where no background experience exists to conduct them.
- Ability to fulfill tasks in limited time frame, and under stressful environments. And can handle multiple tasks with different priorities, while insuring Quality of work.
- Computer literate, with excellent familiarity with Microsoft Office and architectural programs.
- Quick learner, with excellent ability to search for knowledge and depend on own.
- Languages, Arabic (mother language) very good English (reading, writing speaking), French Language (basics).
- Working with good abilities on(AutoCAD Photoshop all Microsoft applications)
- Financial Planning and Strategy, Marketing Concepts, Positioning,
- People Management
- Territory Management
- Sales Planning, Competitive Analysis, Understanding the Customer

- Product Development, Client Relationships, Creative Services,
- Team Leader, One team work
- Abilities to work under pressure, Meeting the company rule,
- Long-term relationship management

## **Work Experience**

# International Red Cross Committee (ICRC), Iraq July 2016 - Now Head of Purchasing Unit

Managing and mentoring a dynamic team of purchasing professionals. Establishing and maintaining measurable performance metrics for all levels of procurement activities to include but not limited to supplier performance, supplier quality, internal order placement performance, buyer activity levels, financial performance, and material shortage elimination.

Report to management the measurable status of progress and corrective actions as it pertains to supplier performance. Ensure performance improvement and recovery plans are developed, issued, tracked and reported on as required for supply base management and improvement.

Negotiate and execute purchase orders or vendor contracts as needed to support the critical business needs.

Strategically develop and implement commodity/supply chain strategies covering all commodities, services and supplier processes throughout a global enterprise to deliver maximum value, leverage, and standardization.

Lead a global enterprise organization within the scope of the strategic sourcing process to drive cost out of the supply chain by managing the following: Commodity and negotiation strategies including Terms and Conditions Supplier selection/de-selection, evaluation and rationalization of Supply chain solutions,

Drives usage of cost models to validate commodity strategies and to understand significant cost drivers. Manages all activities that develop relationships with suppliers.

Develops an overall vendor base which creates and sustains a competitive advantage, utilizing global market exploitation, leveraging spend, and leveraging of technologies.

Provides commodity support to New Program Teams as required to meet target costs and establish program cost models.

Manages materials savings initiatives in line with profit plan and overall business objectives.

## Baghdad Company, Iraq Commercial and contracting Manager

July 2014-June 2016

Serve as the point of contact for customers on contractual matters. Act as contractual "middleman" between company and customers, ensuring timely review and approval / reconciliation of variations. On all standard and nonstandard contracts, provide redlined recommendations and often negotiate directly with customer attorneys or purchasing staff until consensus has been reached Maintain contractual records and documentation such as receipt and control of all contract correspondence, customer contact information sheets, contractual changes, status reports and other documents for all projects. As needed, provide guidance on contract matters to project managers or other operational staff, including training to new project managers and other employees in contracting practices and procedures. Develop and implement procedures for contract management and administration in compliance with company policy. As appropriate, contribute to or influence company policies. Monitor compliance by company employees with established procedures. Work with Risk Management Department / Finance to coordinate contractual insurance requirements. Monitor customer satisfaction with terms and conditions and contracting practices. Ensure that signed contracts are communicated to all relevant parties to provide contract visibility and awareness, interpretation to support implementation. Handle on-going issue and change

## Petrojet Company, Jordan & Iraq Planning & Supply Chain Manager

Aug 2012 – July 2014

Review or update supply chain practices in accordance with new or changing environmental policies, standards, regulations, or laws. Select transportation routes to maximize economy by combining shipments or consolidating warehousing and distribution. Diagram supply chain models to help facilitate discussions with customers. Develop material costs forecasts or standard cost lists.

Assess appropriate material handling equipment needs and staffing levels to load, unload, move, or store materials. Appraise vendor manufacturing ability through on-site visits and measurements.

Analyze inventories to determine how to increase inventory turns, reduce waste, or optimize customer service.

#### HZE Company, Jordan

Jan 2011 – Aug 2012

# Planning & following up Manager Procurement & Logistics Manager

Manage and support the process of selecting suppliers of goods and services (bid solicitation, bid evaluation and award of contracts/P.O.s) for all phases of the project. Interface with engineering, construction, operations, finance, HSE, legal, and insurance as well as Contractors, inspectors, expediters and freight forwarders to insure orders/contracts are placed and completed on schedule. Monitor the contractor procurement function through project completion and turnover, long lead purchase orders/contracts including inspection services, expediting, freight forwarding, shipping and logistics, customs and clearance, taking action as required to ensure project/operational schedules are met. Resolve complex delivery, quality or other related problems with manufacturers and suppliers. Represent the Company to meet contractual requirements. Understand and require contractors to meet all applicable environmental and safety standards. Plan, coordinate and actively participate in meetings with potential suppliers, contractors and user groups. Lead or assist with price negotiations, terms and conditions resolution and quality requirements. Stay abreast of and evaluate current market conditions and develop new sources of supply as necessary.

#### Alnajem altareq Company

Sales and Marketing manager

Sep 2008 — Jan 2011

Achieves marketing and sales operational objectives by contributing marketing and sales information and recommendations to strategic plans and reviews, preparing and completing action plans, implementing production, productivity, quality, and customerservice standards, resolving problems, completing audits, identifying trends; determining system improvements, implementing change, meets marketing and sales financial objectives by forecasting requirements; preparing an annual budget, scheduling expenditures, initiating corrective actions, determines annual and grossprofit plans by forecasting and developing annual sales quotas for regions, projecting expected sales volume and profit for existing and new products, analyzing trends and results, establishing pricing strategies, recommending selling prices, monitoring costs, competition, supply, and demand. Accomplishes marketing and sales objectives by planning, developing, implementing, and evaluating advertising, merchandising, and trade promotion programs; developing field sales action plans. Identifies marketing opportunities by identifying consumer requirements; defining market, competitor's share, and competitor's strengths and weaknesses; forecasting projected business; establishing targeted market share.

Improves product marketability and profitability by researching, identifying, and capitalizing on market opportunities; improving product packaging; coordinating new product development. Sustains rapport with key accounts by making periodic visits; exploring specific needs; anticipating new opportunities. Provides information by collecting, analyzing, and summarizing data and trends. Protects organization's value by keeping information confidential.

## Al-Bir Alameen Company

Sep 2006 — Sep 2008

#### **Civil Engineer (Material Controller)**

Selecting the best combination of materials for specific purposes; testing materials to assess how resistant they are to heat, corrosion analyzing data; assessing materials for specific qualities (such as electrical conductivity, durability, renew ability); advising on the adaptability of a plant to new processes and materials; working to solve problems arising during the manufacturing process or with the finished product, such as those caused by daily wear and tear or a change of environment; supervising quality control throughout the construction and production process; monitoring plant conditions and material reactions during use; helping to ensure that products comply with national and international legal and quality standards; advising on inspection, maintenance and repair procedures; liaising with colleagues in manufacturing, technical and scientific support, supervising the work of materials engineering technicians and other staff; considering the costs implications of materials used and alternatives, in terms of both time and money;

## **Education and Training**

CTP (Cash Transfer Program) Sulymania Iraq	2017
JDE program training Amman –Jordan Erbil - Iraq	2016
Master Degree in business administration (MBA) (NYIT University – Amman / Jordan)	2006-2008

Leadership and management Course 2007

B.SC civil Engineering 2002-2006

(Baghdad University – Baghdad/Iraq)

References available on request